Okay, well, so where market making meets market microstructure is, these are two concepts that sort of work very much hand in hand.
And this is a little, you know, the only clip art or visual that I've made myself.
And, you know, by taking these three pictures and sticking them together.
But essentially, when I think of market making, I think of this job that, you know, a market maker comes into work every day.
And, you know, the beginning of these Brownian motions might be the price of an asset at the beginning of the day.
And 100 here is the end of the day.
And I think of these traders or market makers doing this every day and sort of dealing with this risk.
Essentially, if they're long or short, you know, there's going to be some risk involved.
And the job of a market maker is to post bids and offers in these markets to provide liquidity.
and the way we thought of this model
as a building block, when we first
thought of what the market making
problem was, we really thought in terms of these one
day of Brownian motions and how should a trader
ride these Brownian motions to buy at the bid and
sell at the ask. And then
you'll see that in the first half of the talk, when I focus on market making,
we won't put too much of a lens on this price and what it means.
We'll just look at these paths and call them the mid-price.
And then in the second part of the talk, I'll sort of question that assumption.
Like, is the mid-price really a great notion of fair price?
Should we be thinking of other prices?
And then that's when you need to zoom in and get your hands a bit dirty and actually learn the rules of trading and how it happens with these little tick sizes and bids and offers and arrival of orders.
And, you know, a very kind of strange, chaotic thing that happens at the micro scale.
So in a way
This talk could have been called A tale of two timescales One timescale on the left Which is the one timescale and one timescale on the right which is what if you zoom in to the
millisecond or to the second and start looking at what's happening
there. So it's maybe, if you're physics-minded,
this could be, you could think of the
analyzing waves from
afar and then zooming in and realizing that they're particles.
So in a way, when I talk about, when I think of where market making
meets market microstructure, I think of the same thing
that looks very different when you zoom in.
All right. So
first off, since we just started, maybe
some of you have some ideas about what
market making is, but I'm going to go real basic for people who don't really know necessarily what
it is. So the what, the how, and the why. Okay, so the first question, what is market making?
So very soon I'll go a little bit into what it was, but the way I would like to answer the
question, what is market making today, is I will say it's an algorithm that updates bids and asks
quotes and that's where I'm going to leave it at.
At the very most basic
you can think of someone turning on a computer in the morning and
turning it off at night and hopefully there's more money at the
end of the day than at the beginning of the day. Now how
does that work? That's where we need to start thinking
about state variables, what
what are optimal strategies, what exactly is happening,
and ultimately how market making works.
I'll break it down a little bit more later,
but it's essentially knowing what the fair price is or the right price,
then knowing, developing your personal version of what the right price is,
and then putting a little premium, you know, subtracting a little bit,
calling that your bid and adding a little bit and calling that your ask and following this price around in order.
And then finally the why Why market making Well the root need for market making is to provide liquidity And it sounds a bit vague provide liquidity You know is that good bad We don know
Well, ultimately, the way I would like to think of it is it provides immediacy to another trader that doesn't have time to stick around all day looking at a chart that's moving.
OK, so essentially we need someone and this someone is, in fact, nowadays an algorithm to be there all the time to provide the luxury for us to be able to buy and sell whenever we want.
All right, so now that I've sort of defined the basics of market making, I think it's good to go a little bit into into the past and in fact into the 80s.
This is Wall Street in the 1980s.
And I think it's sort of fun to look at this picture because, you know, when you just see numbers on a screen, you lose the idea that this is a market and you lose the idea that this is the interaction between many agents.
So if you look at these, in fact, if you look at this area of this market, it really kind of looks like the kind of markets where we buy fruits and vegetables and, you know, go on our weekend to get fresh stuff.
there's one really fundamental difference why we don't call these guys just merchants or sales
people is that on top of their wares you know clearly this is a stock market they're buying
they're selling stocks there's sort of always two prices there's the price at which these market
makers will buy and there's a price at which they will sell and i think that is sort of interesting
to see that in a usual market, you can't bring your fish and sort of sell them so that they'll
be sold later.
It's purely a selling business.
And these, what makes market, what defines for me a market maker is the two-sided nature
of the spine.
Now maybe I admit someone All right so this is a Hong Kong stock exchange in the 90s So you can see in 10 years you know quite a bit has changed
There's a lot of more computers per person and this is starting to become automated.
and I think of these pictures as telling a very interesting story
about how the colorfulness and the humanity of these markets
is kind of disappearing a little bit and getting automated.
And in fact, if you look at your typical market today,
this is probably the way it looks, not a fly,
a very cold sort of rational environment,
a data center that might be either in Jersey
or some other outskirts of the financial city.
All right.
So now that we've done our pictures,
let me go through a little bit of that history,
but in terms of the academic papers on market making.
So the paper that sort of inspired Marco and I the most was this Ho and Stahl market maker paper, which was essentially an inventory problem.
And they developed, you know, already in the 80s, a really nice framework that resembles ours quite a bit.
It has some utility functions.
It has some Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equations, and it has some really quite complicated formulas that indicate the mechanics behind a dealer.
And in fact, the dealers at the time were called specialists.
I think the people I was pointing at were specialists, though I'm not 100% sure.
But the specialists were monopolists.
monopolists. So for several certain stocks, only one person was the go-to person that provided a
bid and an ask. And that's quite a different environment than the one that was already
single person putting bids and offers, but rather a wide
variety of agents putting bids and offers and competing for
trades. And so
another twist that ultimately
helped this paper is that we made some approximations that gave a
rather intuitive formula for how this automated
market maker might be programmed.
And so what we see afterwards, we see, you know, this next paper here in 2012 did something quite interesting, which is it bounded the inventory.
So it sort of took an even more realistic risk control, which market makers have, which is you cannot go outside of certain risk bounds.
and that helped the mathematics quite a bit and it rendered it a lot more
rigorous. They were able to prove existence
and uniqueness of solutions and they were also able to show
that this simplifies to a system of ODs
if not a closed form solution, something a lot easier to
handle. And then we have some
many nice generalizations. In 2014
the incorporation of price impact and adverse selection in the market maker
and the multi-asset case in 2017.
And this paper actually has many other twists, bells and twists.
So I would say this 2017 paper by Dion is a great way to start, really,
in this literature if you want to take a look.
And then there's this recent case which incorporates stochastic volatility
which, you know, I'm fast forwarding a little bit to the later part of the talk,
where actually there are many open source versions of this market making code that are being used in cryptocurrencies.
And in cryptocurrencies, the volatility can blow up very fast.
And in fact, you know, the bells and whistles that have been added to these markets, you know, take into account the idea that volatility can be very, very bursty.
All right So market making you know what the main idea well I like this this meme quite a lot because I often feel like this guy whenever I talk to people about their ideas on finance
which is that yes if the idea doesn't boil down to I want to buy low and sell high it's probably
not a great idea but you know the devil is a little bit in the details and and I'm gonna
try to provide the answer to these questions from the point of view
of a market maker who naturally buys,
sets buys and sells at the same time, and therefore, by definition,
the buy is lower than the sell.
The only difference here is, in this meme, it seems like
you would buy low, wait a few days, then sell
high. The only word that
I would change here is days and change it to minutes or seconds. And essentially, that's sort
of the magic idea behind market making. All right, so how do they make money? Well, I'm going to try
and break it down into a few steps. First, it's this idea that you will make the bid-ask spread
times the volume that you trade, at least in the best case scenario. And the other challenge is,
well, you got to do put set your bid-ask spread around the right price.
So if people are trading down here and you're setting your bids and your asks way above it, it's just not realistic.
So the prices you quote need to be relative to an actual price that other people are trading at.
And, you know, I would say that something that every market maker is keenly aware of is that they need to manage their inventory.
So inventory meaning the number of shares, if it's stock, that they have.
And essentially, the ideal position is to be flat.
So think of a market maker as someone who can be long X and short X, but not really wants to stay within these bounds and prefers being at zero.
And the way the inventory is reduced is again by bullet point number two by quoting around the correct the right price level Okay so you know in this sort of you know if you want if you don you know
if you want to use the minimal amount of math to express the idea of a market maker,
I think you would look at this kind of equations.
First of all, what's the right price?
My first answer, my first stab at this is going to be the mid price.
and then I'm going to contradict myself
in 30 minutes or so,
but for the next 30 minutes,
the right price to first order
will be the market mid price.
And then to second order,
I will need to adjust my personal
or my reservation price
with respect to this mid price.
And the way I'll do it is
with minus beta Q,
Q being my inventory.
So if I'm long,
I'm going to, my personal valuation will be a bit lower because I'm desperate to sell really.
And if I'm short, my personal valuation will be a bit higher than this mid price because I want to buy.
So this is sort of, this is the main mechanism of inventory management really.
And then because this would imply that you're buying and selling at the same price and that doesn't obey the law of buy low, sell high.
So market makers typically ask for a premium below and above this reservation price.
So R minus delta and R plus delta.
And for now, I'm not going to worry too much what beta and delta are.
And really, the reason to frame this into an optimization problem is to hopefully tease out what this beta and delta should be and what should it depend on.
All right, so now I'm going to step into sort of the world of optimization and specifically stochastic optimization.
So let's start with just a few state variables we're going to need.
So the first one is just this, you know, this essentially a Brownian motion.
It represents the price of the stock.
and for now we're going to think of this as the mid-price.
And so you know essentially think of these as one day of trading on a pretty volatile asset Okay so this is the price but unlike most models let say the Black model or other models that allow for dynamic trading here you will not be allowed to trade at this mid
and there's no
it's not a fixed transaction cost
model but rather it's a model where
you stick your bid
slightly below and you're
asked slightly above this mid price
and the question is by how much
and so
why
what is the optimization
or what it
I might need to shift this
to the side a bit
hopefully
go away yeah
yes okay beautiful all right so so you're the idea here and maybe the picture is where we should
start is that this blue line is the mid price and the orange line is the ask price and the
The green one is the bid price.
And so a market maker, to be noticed, needs to follow this mid-price around.
And the main mechanism of trading is that if you're very close to the mid-price, you see a lot of trading.
If you're far away, forget about it.
You're not going to get any trades.
So the mechanism here is that the buy orders arrive with a Poisson rival rate with intensity lambda.
And this lambda depends on how far your bid is from the mid price.
And it decays exponentially.
So essentially, a market maker that squeezes around the bid and the ask, you know, by, let's say, one cent and follows it everywhere.
we'll see a lot more trades
than one that does the same with two cents.
We'll see a lot more trades
than someone who does it with three cents, et cetera.
So if you know a lot about order books,
don't worry too much because this has some problems.
But in terms of, think of it as a market with a certain supply
and a certain demand around people competing with you
to supply these limit orders, it sort of does make sense
that there needs to be some kind of, in all optimization problems,
you win some, you lose some.
If you're further away from the mid, you will each make more money each time you trade, but you'll trade rarely.
And if you're close to the mid, you'll trade a lot, but each time you'll make a tiny little amount.
So that's the interplay or that's where the optimization will come in.
All right.
So what's the objective?
Here we have a sort of a classic-ish maximization of expected utility.
So negative e to the negative gamma of this term here is just a utility function.
This also reminds me of my first talk at NYU when I first arrived fresh as a fresh PhD graduate.
And I had a lot to say about utility functions.
And I didn't get booed offstage, but there was a lot of, you know, dislike with utility functions.
And, in fact, we put in a lot of effort in this paper to make the utility functions disappear.
So hopefully, you know, this doesn't throw you off too much.
But think of it as a one parameter family given by gamma, where gamma going to zero is risk neutral.
and the larger the gamma, the more risk-averse you are.
And this is basically just a concave increase in function.
All right.
But, you know, I could, yeah.
Yeah, so we'll see at the end when we get the results,
we can just set
gamma to zero
and see what we get.
But essentially
what you'll see
is that
as gamma goes to zero,
the trader will care will not care about inventory anymore So the risk of the price moving will be unimportant because the stock price is as likely to go up as to go down
and the market maker will not care.
So, yes, absolutely.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
So, for example, if you quote a very tight spread, this risk will be a bit less worrisome because the other side will come quite often.
But if you have very wide spreads, indeed, you go long and then you may never go short again.
So go back to that.
So what's inside of the utility function?
Let's just look at this is essentially the wealth of the trader at time T.
And we're going to think of capital T as the end of the day and little t as right now or in the middle of or beginning or middle of the day.
So the utility function here is over the cash you will have at time T.
And QS is the quantity of stocks times the price.
So basically the value of your inventory.
So at the end of the day, all that matters is the value of what you're sitting on.
So this is your P&L.
It's the cash P&L plus the inventory P&L.
And so the cash P&L evolves in a very simple way.
So every time you sell, you add PA to your pile of cash.
And every time you buy, you add, you subtract PV from your pile of cash.
And the quantity or your inventory simply goes up when you buy and it goes down when you sell.
So those are basically the dynamics of X, Q.
And we already saw that the dynamics of S is just a Brownian motion.
you
Yes, that's what I mean.
So the arrival of orders are – so I think that our market maker is only trading with a fraction of the total number of trades.
And so, in fact, if they're far away from the mid, it's a tiny fraction, like maybe 1% of the volume.
And if it's close to zero, close to the mid price, then you're participating in almost every trade.
And these dynamics are the trades that the market maker sees, not every trade in the order book.
Sure.
yes so in fact i think of zero as the the ideal position but later on when we go into
a market making in cryptocurrencies uh market makers typically have two coins that they need to
trade in and there the target might be 0.5 or
half of your budget. So I think that
in the first half of the talk, think of the
ideal scenario to be flat and have zero inventory.
yeah or you can think of maybe this market maker having
an optimal position that they want to to revert around and you know uh so yeah so yeah there's
many twists and generalizations of this. I think
for simplicity, let's think of zero as the ideal
position.
So these...
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Thank you All right
This is very interesting.
So, technically, at the end of the day, XT plus QST may not be quite as safe as XT plus 0ST.
Why?
because there's an overnight move that could be gigantic.
So in fact, this model will have a certain counterintuitive feature
that the trader will be more risk averse at the beginning of the day
and will be willing to take on strange inventory positions at the end of the day.
So that is definitely something we, I don't know if you would say was messed up,
But you could definitely include QXT plus QT plus one ST plus one.
And there, if you had this extra source of noise for the overnight move, you'd find that the market maker might behave quite different.
So, yeah, good question.
And in fact, in the world of cryptocurrencies, I keep giving you these sneak previews.
They never close.
So very often people will adapt this model to an infinite horizon or want to make the time T disappear.
So rather, they're looking for time insensitive strategies.
Why do I assume a Poisson?
Ah, well, because a lot of this technology here that's going to, the magic that happens between posing an optimal utility problem and then writing an equation that you're able to solve, which is this Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation, this requires a Markov assumption.
And so if you're ever going to have models with jumpiness and you want Markov, then really Poisson is sort of the way to go.
tractable because, to be honest, these equations are not extremely tractable. So how do we get this
equation if you've never seen anything like this before? Well, what you do is you use the dynamic
programming principle, which is that if you want to maximize, optimize this between little time t
and capital T, you need to do it over the next delta t and then be optimal at t plus delta t
onward and then you take a limit and these limits give you these partial differential equations
and in fact when there's question so the the ugliest term you know maybe if you've seen the
black shells ed this term doesn't scare you much but these jumpy terms are sort of at the heart
of this problem because what you have is you have these utilities um that that uh these differences
of utilities. And this is
not a very standard PDE.
In this case, it ends up being very hard to solve
unless you make some assumptions on the boundedness
of the inventory. But I won't get too much into
technical details just to show you that
the idea is to set up a problem in a probabilistic
sense and then turn it into a deterministic differential equation.
And then, you know, these are very, like, quite hard to solve numerically.
So, you know, one way to overcome this is to take asymptotic expansions.
And essentially, what I'm showing you here is an approximation to the solution of this
Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation.
And this solution, you'll recognize a few features or things that I desired about my market making earlier on, but with a few more parameters that we can now discuss.
So first of all, there's the idea that the bid and ask prices are given by premiums above and below a reservation price, and that this reservation price is something that takes the mid price and tilts it in the direction opposite to your inventory.
And then
The The The extra things To discuss are Okay what is the beta Or what is this sensitivity of the price with respect to the inventory And here we see that it proportional to your risk aversion and to your inventory risk
Or rather, and you can see that this depends on time to the end of the day.
so in fact
you tilt things more aggressively
at the beginning of the day than at the end of the day
something which many market
makers would want to see reversed
but
you know
the other interesting thing is that
the premiums around
the mid
the premiums that the market maker has to
set around
its reservation
price
has two terms, one that depends on the volatility
and basically the risk of this asset,
and the other which only depends on the microstructure.
So this K, if you remember, was the rate at which you're trading decays
as you go further and further from the mid.
So think of this as the risk component of the spread
and think of this as the microstructure component of the spread.
And somehow the two are a little bit tied together by this risk aversion parameter.
But, you know, this is essentially the formulas that in more recent years have seen a little revival.
So, OK, before I get into this cryptocurrency stuff that I'm sure you're all very excited to hear about, let me...
Yeah.
Yeah, but the tilting...
So yeah, the question is,
it about the behavior of the market maker towards the end of the day And you know you hinting that there are certain aspects that are attractive about this
i.e. the spread, the bid-ask spread of the market maker gets tighter towards the end,
hence helping them get out of their position.
But the tilting up and down around the mid-price is less and less aggressive.
We'll see what this, you know, I have a very simple simulation
going on here, essentially Brownian motions plus some Poisson arrivals that illustrate a little bit
what is happening. So first the inventory. So you see that the inventory starts at zero and stays
within pretty tight bounds. However, the behavior in these simulations is that bigger inventories
kind of creep up towards the end of the day. So this may not be ideal if you really want a zero
position at the end of the day. In fact, many market makers
remove that dependency on time and replace T minus T by
a constant. And then this would look
much more like a tunnel and most of your inventories would be
really tightly controlled throughout the day.
Another illustration is that if you
plot the P&L, in other words,
Remember the cash plus the quantity of stocks times the stock price
So essentially your mark-to-market P&L
Then you see that this has a positive drift
And that it's relatively tight
In other words, there aren't that many losses
So obviously this is a simulation
don't get too encouraged to start up your market making business tomorrow.
But I don't want to discourage you either.
So we'll go into the more realistic.
In fact, I don't think I want to talk that much about this
other than showing you that this very highly peaked P&L
is the strategy that I was showing you earlier,
which is controls for risk.
And this is compared to another strategy that I call the symmetric strategy which is we all you know there a profit maximizing spread for a risk neutral agent which is essentially do find the distance away from the mid that creates the most P per unit of time
And if you do that, you'll see that you'll get the P&L in blue, but you'll find that your inventory will go out of control.
So potentially could lead to very big wins, but also very big losses.
In other words, this is one of the most important constraints of a market maker is this control of inventory.
Yeah.
might be that
you're looking for
fireworks
during one day
not a
yeah
so what
you are
doing
is
you're
only going
to
direct
something
that is
not a
model
like
a
cell
but a market maker
shall allow it to be
sized externally
one by fifty
but it's supposed to be one by one
I'm not
but there are some papers that have
tackled exactly that
so there are versions
of this that allow
for variable quantities
and that's another way of controlling
inventory
And there are also some of these papers that include trends that may last for a small amount of time
And alpha signals
There are definitely some bells and whistles that we can add to that
And in fact, so right now I'm going to
Right. So the shift can. So there are two reasons you may shift away up and down the mid price.
The first reason might be you think or you see maybe in the order book trends through your signal analysis.
The other one is you have an inventory that asks you to tilt.
So there's the there's the microstructure or, you know, let's say price prediction problem.
And then there's the inventory management problem. And I think that's.
So far, I've only really talked about the inventory control problem.
And now I'm going to show you some results related to live trading.
So a few months ago, I had some entrepreneurs from a cryptocurrency market-making company that sent me an email and wanted to talk to me.
And ultimately, they ended up telling me, oh, have you heard of this company called Hummingbot?
And they turned me on to the idea, to the fact that in this open source software called Hummingbot,
there are many market making algorithms that are open source and that people can download and use themselves.
And apparently one of the popular models is this Aveaneda-Stoykov model that seems to be sort of very much used by many crypto companies.
The idea being that when crypto coins come into existence, they need to make everyone feel secure that there's a two-sided market for this.
and they hire companies to do market making for them
and even give them maybe a portion of the total amount of coins to do this job.
And this person was kind of hinting that actually many of them
just sort of use the Ape and Edda Stoikov model and call it a day.
And essentially this company was interested in sort of making this type of trading
available to more people
and sort of
have a crowdsource
of market makers if you will So here a nice picture that I saw I think it sort of says it all This is a Bitcoin price chart that I found And you know you can see that this is a pretty illiquid market It goes through very erratic drops
And what you see, the colors here are limit buy orders and limit sell orders that are being updated in the order book.
And the color scheme, I think, is just the size of the order.
But if you follow some of these little sort of stripes around, you see that it seems like there are some market makers that are hugging the price a little bit like in this Poisson arrival model and sort of following it around and waiting to get lucky and essentially hoping to make this bid-ask spread.
So I think this is pretty interesting that you can see this on cryptocurrency markets with your naked eye, because in almost any other order book that I've seen that are much denser and where you can't tell one trader apart from the other, you don't really see this kind of behavior of market makers following the price.
So it's kind of a nice example.
And in fact, I sort of think that maybe the model in our paper was maybe more appropriate for cryptocurrencies
than stocks or futures or more liquid assets,
specifically because, all right, there's something that I think some people would call it a product-market fit.
It's, you know, this model sort of implicitly assumes that there's a lot of wiggle room for your tilting of your quotes.
And in most order books, there isn't.
You're either at the top of the book or you're not there.
So I think that one of the reasons I've rationalized that people in cryptocurrencies care about this model is because it sort of seems to have been made for it before cryptocurrencies existed.
So I find that kind of amusing.
So anyways, you can go to this Hummingbot website.
It's very simple.
There's 12 different ways you can download it.
Yep.
So the question is Why is this model more suitable for crypto than other markets So essentially the point I going to try to make for the second half of this talk is that the tick size in cryptocurrencies is extremely small
And what that means is that there are many empty slots where you can put an order and have no competition.
most other markets have large queues at every price and and this idea that you will trade if
you're seven ticks away from the mid is impossible so so in some some of the critiques uh we've had
for this this um market making algorithm is that it doesn't really work let's say on a futurist
market or the S&P 500 or
ETFs and stocks that are very large
where the fixed size is very large. If you don't know what I mean by large and small fixed size,
I'll get into it very soon.
All right. So
here's what happens when you first launch this
code. And this code is all open source. So if there's one line of code in there
that you want to change a little bit,
it's very easy to recompile it and then run with it.
What it first asks you is,
what's your market-making strategy?
So here I picked the AVE and ADA market-making.
The second thing it asks you is,
what's your data source?
And I had to create a Qcoin account for this to work.
What's your trading pair?
Bitcoin USD.
what's the time frame
infinite, you know, this is the idea that this T minus T is just
replaced by a number. Then the amount of Bitcoin
per order, so this is the trade size
the risk aversion
and then there's a parameter which is not in the model but it's an
implementation issue is how often do you cancel
and replace your quotes.
So the frequency of updates here, 10 seconds.
And then you have to give it your inventory target.
So your ideal amount.
So your ideal amount in when you trade cryptocurrencies
is not zero and you can really go short To my knowledge you can really go short in these markets So really you put 50 to say that you know you want to keep your inventory at half Bitcoin half USD And then it creates
a little configuration file. And it says, press start to, you know, you can look at this
configure. So look at the configuration file. Essentially, this is a sort of a very simple
heuristic that populates all of the
parameters in the model.
And ultimately, when you just press start, it's sort of
and this is paper trading, so I haven't really put any real money
behind this, at least not yet. And this is
sort of what the status at any point during the day while
you're running it, you know, here's your balance
Essentially, right now the inventory is 54% Bitcoin.
We wanted 50-50, and it's 45% USD.
And so there's a mid-price.
Here's a reservation price, which is a little bit lower because we have too much Bitcoin, so we want to sell it.
Essentially, this is right now seems kind of intuitive.
There's a spread of $4 around the mid-price.
And another twist is that this estimates the volatility in real time.
So right now the volatility is this point, double or 9%.
If volatility goes up, it does adjust it.
So think of it as using your Black-Scholes formula.
And even though it's based on a fixed volatility, people can use it however they like.
And here they like to widen their spreads as volatility goes up, which I think is sensible.
All right. So first, the good news, you know, at the end, it spits out a bunch of hypothetical trades that you would have done.
And the way it does that is rather simple. At every point in time, it keeps track of where your bid and your ask is.
And if it sees any trades in the market that are below your bid or above your ask, boom, you're assumed to be executed.
0.1, so we see that this market maker kind of
stays neatly within plus or minus five trades
around zero. That's the good news.
Not as good news was when I started calculating my P&L.
I realized that this algorithm never had a
chance. Also, to be
perfectly honest, I also closed my laptop a few times and may have
done this over the course of a few days so the big drawdowns maybe are not you know could be
taken away but ultimately this thing goes down quite severely all right why why is that well
uh the first is a genuinely good excuse the price of bitcoin went down over this time and i was
aiming at a 50% long Bitcoin. So, okay, I suffered just that downturn. So that's one answer. It's not
the whole answer. My other excuse is I didn't mess around with parameters at all. I never
really, I just put in a few random numbers and pressed play. I'm told by some of the people who
who wrote these algorithms that they run, you know, 10 or 20 of them in parallel and kind of, you know, keep the data.
And, you know, they fine tune these things and they find where their parameters should be.
But the good news is inventory was kept under control.
And I think that the more honest answer of why this didn't work is that the mid price does not have a lot of information.
So if, and now I'm going to take you on a little,
let's see how much time I have for this,
a little adventure in microstructure,
maybe to try to see what can we do,
essentially answer this question,
can we do better than the mid price?
Yeah, we have a question.
Good question.
I think it might be a setting.
I didn't really pay attention to that, to the training.
My guess is.
So you do.
So in many markets you get rebates for being a market maker In these exchanges like binance or qcoin uh they don really give you rebates so who will pay you actually the owners of the coin
will sometimes pay certain people to keep uh market making uh and that that is that could
be a source of revenue but as a little player jumping in the order book no one's paying you
for that. So my guess is that
but you do pay, yeah, so unlike
the stock markets where you get rebate for limit orders and pay for
trading, these cryptocurrency exchanges typically charge
both people. And they give you a discount if you trade very high
volumes. All right, so let me
yeah.
So I was net long
So during
The settings that I chose
Here
Were 50-50
So I was aiming at a 50-50
Bitcoin USD
Balance
In the stock markets
It's very easy to go short and long, or it's much easier.
And therefore, the ideal place to be is at zero.
In cryptocurrency markets, typically, people are between two coins.
Yeah.
And in fact, this is Bitcoin USDT.
if I did Bitcoin, Ethereum, maybe this would be even safer because if I had to 50-50, maybe, I don't know, maybe there would be a bit of diversification.
But it's a very risky asset class for sure.
So this was the bad news.
And let's try to see what's the hope.
or if I were to spend a lot of energy on these
open source codes, how would I improve them? So let's
think a little bit about this. So this gets me
into my second topic of the day, which is market microstructure.
It a little bit harder to define It a bit of a different people will define it differently To me market microstructure is the mechanisms of trading
So being interested in how, and this includes the venues of trading,
so the rules of these venues.
It also includes the sort of, you know,
analysis of the participants of trading.
It's kind of an intersection between the motivations that makes people trade
and the places where they end up trading.
So it could be now it's dominated by limit order books is the most common mechanism for trading.
But there are also dark pools.
You know, there are many venues you can trade at.
And then there are market makers, but they're just one of many participants.
There are some people who trade very differently from market makers.
Now, how, you know, how do people use market making?
Well, you know, I may be a bit biased, but I think that one of the big motivations,
or not motivation, but the outcomes of market-making papers is,
oh, well, by studying this venue and these actors,
I can make prediction about the price.
And then, you know, you might say that's the ultimate goal of market microstructure
is it to predict future prices.
And I would say maybe why, and again, this is kind of a personal take,
I think that all of market microstructure wants to explain away all the mechanics of trading to come to the essence of what the fair price is.
And so this fair price sometimes is called the fair price.
Sometimes it's called the true price.
Sometimes it's called the efficient price.
Sometimes it's called the micro price.
So these are all different terms that are thrown around for this kind of a holy grail of like, how do I get through all this mess of people jumping around in this venue to the fair price?
And so this is kind of the. Yeah.
Zero to one Yeah I suppose
I mean, in the same way that $100 bills on the floor tend to disappear,
but I still will pick them up if I see them.
But so yeah, so this, this, the barrier to entry is extremely low so it took me not much time to lose all this money on paper.
so the i think that uh you know and today i'm going to provide you with one idea to improve
this i don't know if this idea will will save this strategy it might take three or four ideas
to make this work and then whoever gets the fifth idea probably will take most of the money so so
yeah i i do agree that this is a very easy um or you know there's another risk which is that this
whole cryptocurrency, all these coins are going to collapse.
And then, you know, that's a genuine risk here.
So this is kind of one of my, it gives me the chance to say one of my favorite jokes,
which is there are two kinds of people, the kind of people who think there are two kinds
of people and the others.
And so obviously
There's actually a whole spectrum of market microstructures
And there's a lot of variables across which we could look
It's just that I find that large tick size and small tick size
Almost says it all to me
So about the market microstructure
And I like to focus on this as a defining variable
So large tick size just means that
the minimum, the grid upon which you can put prices is relatively large compared to the price.
So think of maybe a grid size, you know, a price of a stock that has a $10 price.
And then think of, you know, a bid-ask spread of one cent.
And that's a rather, it's 10 basis points.
amounts. And if there are lots of buyers and sellers, that is what I call your quintessential
or what is a quintessential large tick size relative to the price. Now, what happens in,
you know, specifically in cryptocurrencies is that these markets seem to not have really
cared much about the grid size. They just made it super small. And as these prices started going up
to 10,000 and 20,000, no one really got the memo that maybe we could change the grid size.
So it stayed tiny.
And of course, there are many markets where the tick size is small.
Other examples are tech stocks that have gone to prices like $2,000.
And even though they're very liquid, do not have a single cent bid-ask spread.
So those are other examples of small tick size stocks.
But I think cryptocurrencies is currently my best example for small tick size.
So who has large tick sizes?
Typically futures, you know, traded on the CME, for example, very large tick sizes.
They're low price stocks just because the bid-ask spread has to be one cent.
So naturally the tick size becomes large.
And then very liquid ETFs or very liquid stocks.
And by liquid, I just mean lots of trading happening.
And these typically have large tick sizes.
And if you look at a chart or a visual of these things, you can see that these horizontal lines show you, you know, it's a visual of the order book.
and it basically shows you that the price is almost always at a one cent tick and
so in green here you see the trades in buy trades in red you see the sell trades and
you really see that this thing is very I guess chunky I would call it it just kind of goes
you can really see when it jumps up and jumps down,
and it doesn't look like a Brownian motion, really.
And here you can see the Q sizes.
And yeah when I look at a picture like this I see large thick size Now what happened or the sort of the main insights to gather from large tick size assets is that the imbalance is king
So I call this the least well-kept secret in high-frequency trading,
which is that if you're going to look at a data set that has bid, ask, bid size, ask size,
at some point you'll figure out that the ratio of bit size to bit size plus ask size
might be something to look at.
And it turns out that it matters quite a lot.
And what I like about this sort of microstructure signal
is that it's not one of these signals that you write a paper about it and it disappears.
This is here to stay.
It's very much part of the structure of large tick order books.
So when the imbalance is close to one,
that means there's let's say a bid size of 100 and an ask size of one that means there's a
tremendous amount of buyers and there's only one seller at the ask this turns out to be something
that everyone loves to jump on and buy so everyone if you see a bid size of 100 and an ask size of
one everyone wants to buy that at that ask so paradoxically the side of the order book where
you see the least liquidity is the one where everyone wants to fight to jump on it.
I used to think that people go where the liquidity is, but actually it is completely reversed.
And, you know, this is empirically true.
There's not a single large stock where I haven't seen this.
There's no dark markets, but there's this thing, these...
decentralized exchanges like Uniswap is one.
I don't know if you've heard about it.
So the question was about dark pools in cryptocurrencies.
And those are, they have implemented a thing called automated market makers,
AMM, which is pools of coins, two coins.
And then people put money in these pools and other people transact with it.
and the people who put the money in get rewards for it so it's sort of like an automatic uh an
even more rule market maker than the one i describing here and i think that in some ways is similar to a dark pool in the mechanics of it But the truth is I never really studied dark pools
and I don't know that much about how they differ
from these cryptocurrency automatic market makers.
Oh, quantity.
So whenever I write QB, I mean the quantity at the bid, and QA is the quantity at the ask.
At the best bid and the best ask, yes.
So those are just, yeah, top of the book imbalance.
And on the SNPE mini, so that's a very liquid future,
you can see that here I'm plotting the imbalance
and conditional on this imbalance
if a trade happens
basically I've accumulated the buy and sell volume
on these imbalances
and you can see very clearly
when the imbalance is close to 1
there's a lot of buy volume happening in these instances
paradoxically on the side that has the least amount of volume
quoted
So this is transaction volume, really.
And then, you know, when the imbalance is small, everyone wants to sell.
So that is, you know, these type of curves, I have yet to see a market where they're not steep in this particular or asymmetric in this particular way.
So that, you know, all it says is pay attention to imbalance.
And if you're going to build a microstructure model on a single factor, well, it's probably this one, especially on large fixed stocks.
So now, why is that interesting?
Well, you can do a few things.
You can use the imbalance as a factor in a model that will predict the price, I don't know, five minutes from now or 10 minutes from now or the next VWAP or some kind.
You can predict anything you want and you'll get many different models that help you build, you know, combine the imbalance with the current price.
This is based on A paper I wrote a few years ago There a way of defining the fair price that I call the microprice that can add a little bit of rigor to well what if you don know the horizon of the fair at which you trying to predict things
And all you want is to ask yourself, what's my fair price right now?
And that's that's so so this is one way of doing it, which which I find interesting.
So the idea is you take a limit of price approximations and your price approximation.
P.I. is the expected mid price of tau.
I tau. I being the I mid price change.
So the first most natural thing you might want to do is you might define your P1, your fair price, as the expected mid price at the moment that the price moves at this random time.
And that in large tick markets will be the current mid plus one tick or the current mid plus one tick or minus one tick.
So it's really a weighted average of two prices.
Now the idea here is
Oh well what about if we go
A little further and fast forward
This movie to the second price
Change well empirically
You'll find that there's a very big
Reversion the price ticks up
It'll often tick right back down
More often than it'll tick up
Twice so that
Suddenly makes you think that
Maybe this
P1 is not as
Accurate as you might want
and maybe you have a slightly longer horizon.
And really, this idea of taking this limit I to infinity is to say,
okay, right now my price, I don't know how to define it.
It's messy.
There's lots of buyers, some sellers, and there's essentially a mid,
but no one can trade at this mid.
So how do I define the fair price?
And the idea is to take, okay, the mid is imperfect now,
But it's a bit more, if I squint and I push it back one time step, it's a bit better.
And if I push it to infinity, you know, the microstructure and the sort of the ugliness of this granular market disappears.
And essentially this is smooth.
Now, this limit doesn't exist by all means
for every model that you might invent. In fact,
if the model, if there's any amount of
predictable trend in this market, the limit as p goes to infinity is
infinity and then the price doesn't converge. So even
defining this requires a lot of symmetry in your
modeling. But here's a, you know, just to give you an idea, because I don't have that much more time,
this is a little bit the type of Markov chains that come around this, that you can compute
micro prices around. Think of three states, a small imbalance, a middle imbalance, and a high
imbalance. And then the price can stay the same and it can bounce around between low, high, and
made imbalance. And at some point, a transition happens and it bumps up or it goes down and it's
sort of absorbed. That's the one-step version. The two-step version of this is the price goes up
and now it has a low imbalance and it may bounce around and go up again or it may bounce back down.
So you can see how maybe this will help you visualize essentially what the price,
how the micro price might be computed through, let's say, a simulation calibrated to data.
And in fact, we've done something like this on some actual data.
So, for example, Bank of America, large tick asset.
You can see that the micro price is essentially the mid price plus an adjustment.
And this adjustment is in cents or in fractions of a cent.
And if the imbalance is low, so maybe focus on the spread equal one tick because Bank of America is 99% of the time is a one tick spread.
You can see when the imbalance is low, you should subtract almost half a cent from the mid price to get the fair price.
In other words, the fair price is close to the bid.
And similarly, when the imbalance is high, you should add half a cent to your fair price.
And what you see here is that if the spread is two ticks this is a lot flatter than you think And in fact so the blue line is the extreme of just the mid price is the fair price so you can see that for a tick size of two if there a two large queues and an empty spot in the middle well most people even if there a
bit of an imbalance view the mid price as the fair price or rather this is what this model
in place. And if you look at Chevron, because now I'm going to want to arrive to Bitcoin,
but halfway there, I'm going to look at Chevron and I'm going to notice something interesting,
which is when Chevron typically trades at two or three cent ticks, at least at the time of this
data set. And when the spread is one tick, which is unusually small, then you can see that the
the imbalance has a large impact on how much you should adjust your mid-buy.
However, for a four tick spread, which is unusually large for Chevron,
then the imbalance says less or is less meaning.
So maybe, you know, now I'm going to try and make a leap of faith and say,
OK, what would it be in Bitcoin?
Well, I imagine that in Bitcoin, maybe there's a spread that's multiple tick sizes.
And if that's the case, then maybe my imbalance at the top of the book has no meaning.
And now I really may need to care about deeper in the book what's going on.
And so this is a picture of Bitcoin.
I'm going to accelerate a little bit.
Let me just say that this is actually a very thin order book.
The lowest price here to the upper price is actually $100.
dollars. And so this may seem, oh, there's a lot of size, but no, this is cumulative sizes. So these
are not populated order books. They're order books with little spikes and deserts in between.
So there's this. So something needs to be done. So now this is a heuristic and this is some work
that I did with some master's students at Cornell Financial Engineering in their thesis last
semester. And they came up with this VAMP.
So VAMP is volume adjusted
mid-price. And the idea is take a parameter
the parameter that it depends on is just Q.
So think of Q as the total amount of dollars you want to buy right now or the total amount of dollars you want to sell So they set Q to something like And then you accumulate on the bid price first all the prices at which an order that sells into the order book would accumulate to
So it could be the first 10 levels, let's say, of the order book.
And then, you know, you weigh, you look at the sizes at each of these queues and you weigh the prices by those size.
So essentially, you pick a size and this size will tell you how deep in the book of a bite you need to take.
And then you're going to take a weighted average of these prices in this big bite, let's say.
And you do the same on the ask side and you get a, you know, a new bid.
We're going to call it the VWAP bid and the VWAP ask.
And actually, we'll find that this VWAP bid and VWAP ask is way wider than the bid ask spread that seems to be rather unnaturally tight.
So here's the idea.
You build this.
Now, they didn't just pull it out of nowhere and then run with it.
they actually showed that the difference between VAMP and the MID is a good predictor of, you know,
whether the asset will go up or down at the various timescales ranging from one second to 60 seconds.
So it seems quite robust.
So, you know, another group of students also wrote a market maker in cryptocurrencies
and took a very simple market maker where essentially the reservation price was just S minus beta Q.
They played around with the parameter beta.
And the bid-ask spread, so delta A plus delta B is the bid-ask spread, was a constant, so not a function of volatility.
So, again, this is a very back-of-the-envelope simple market maker.
and the idea is now
okay, well, we can do a market maker around the mid-price, but we can
also do a market maker around the volume
is vamp or volume adjusted mid-price. And let's see what the P&Ls
how they differ In other words does this sort of microstructure twist maybe adding some alpha to your price does that help And I have to say that the first day or the first time I ran this or rather the first half of the day that I ran this I was super impressed
I thought, wow, this vamp is magical.
Because if you just market make around the mid price, you sort of stay flat.
And if you do it around this different price, which is very easy to compute, you do a whole lot better.
However, running it a little bit more, this is the full day, there was a catastrophic plunge maybe three, four hours into it.
and you know
I just
obviously looked at the price dynamics
and yeah there was a big drop
in the price at that time
that's sort of the enemy number
one of market makers
is these violent changes
in your day to day
it may look good and you can optimize
for a lot of factors and I think
this is sort of what we've done here
but it's a dangerous business
yeah
Yeah, so in this setup, one improvement might be, oh, what if this K and this beta, much
like in the model, we made that
like a function of volatility. So if volatility goes up, my spreads
will go up, my tilting will increase. Maybe that'll save
me a little bit in these tough spots. And so that's actually
how Hummingbot has implemented this. They do
calculate volatility in real time. Does it always save you?
I don't know, because volatility takes a little while to calculate
and it could be too late by the time your volatility has been updated.
of market making.
So it has this, you know,
actually in the nature
of maybe financial engineering
is that very often things
that are built seem like
a regular good money maker,
you know, like picking pennies
in front of a tractor.
And the, you know,
it seems like a good business
until it isn't.
But the problem is that
when it isn't,
it's sort of the end
of your business.
So it's a very, you know,
very exciting business. I like the math
behind it,
but I'm a little bit afraid to put all my
money into it, though
my new crypto
friends would like me
to join them
in their enterprises.
So yeah, this is
all I have for now. If you have any questions,
I'm happy to answer.
Yeah?
Thank you.